[Music]
uh
welcome everybody this is
from learned intel series this episode
we will continue
our topic of diagnosis and treatment
planning and active density
we are still focusing on diagnosis of
dental care
i would like to declare that i don't
receive fees compensation or realities
from the sales of any of the products
shown or discussed in this presentation
also this presentation
has not been sponsored by any company
agency or organization and is only
prepared for educational purposes let me
remind you about this presentation that
is a copyright presentation that could
not be transmitted by any mean unless
you have
written permission from the
author in this presentation today our in
this episode we are still continuing to
correlate between the oral and dental
clinical findings and the proposed
treatment plan also still we are trying
to properly diagnose dental cares by
different techniques
to diagnose early and as as well as the
late
progress of dental cares okay in
previous episodes we already discussed
part 1 patient assessment and
information gathering in terms of
demographic data chief complain and its
history medical history and dental
history then in the second part we
already started the clinical examination
we start to examine dental care is still
we are within the traditional techniques
to diagnose dental care in traditional
techniques we started with visual
examination and still we have some
topics that untouched up to now and
undiscussed up till now we already
discussed the visual examination simply
by light and mirror okay
and then we already assigned and this is
to help or to score the standardization
of visual examination to be
more subjective and to decrease the gap
between
that
transformation of what you have seen
between operator and another by
introducing different indices including
both a system including
icds system including american dental
association
system in all aspects and that's just
for standardized scoring of visual
examination then today we will continue
okay
how to
introduce
techniques to improve
visual examination the visual detection
of dental cares in early stages rather
than naked eye or to help your neck eye
sight view okay to determine exactly or
detect exactly the presence of dental
cares at its third early stage the
simplest
technique advanced technique to advance
visual examination is the magnification
okay to allow the practitioner to
observe the finest detail with great
accuracy and high resolution this
magnification can be achieved by
different techniques including
transmitting
the vision field okay into a monitor
with magnifications just like that of
intra-oral cameras that
allow zooming okay and aided with light
emitting the old light source that will
allow you to properly inspect by vision
your lesion or your field also
magnification loops is available with
different magnification up to
reaching for microscope which provides
you with 20x magnification powers okay
and here in this
table you could find
how much the resolution could be
improved by using magnifying aids okay
and it's each type of magnification each
power of magnification
how much it will improve the resolution
of the field you could see okay this is
an example of intraoral camera to the
left side transmitting
the field or the picture to a monitor
okay that could be zoomed and
was much better lightning at the same
time you have a monitor
to
discuss the case with your patient it
provides much more communication with
your patient because of this monitor
okay to the right side what we have
displayed before in the previous
episodes is a magnification loops either
with overhead light or not okay this is
another way which using microscopy which
is much more important in
endodontics
much more than that for optimum density
it's also useful and helpful in octave
density but it is commonly used with
endodontics okay because it is
beneficial and
its economic visibility from the
visibility of economic uh
part okay
it is much more beneficial than used in
operative density you could then lose
even as you could see in the right side
you could lose even micro cracks okay
and the full details of the cavity
margins then comes what is called trans
illumination trans illumination it is
a source of light
okay
from
the buccal or lingual side of the tooth
and on the other side you will have your
mirror okay just passing the light
through the integrities or the
posteriorities from side to side the
proximal case could be appear as a dark
area even if it is incipient and it will
be shown at a darker area it will help
you to diagnose in cb indicators in
proximate areas it's as simple as you
have a light source from one side and a
mirror to receive the image and just
notes the darkness has appeared in this
uh photograph then
you could perform trans illumination by
two types either simplest one is fibro
optic transient illumination device
which is called 40 as an abbreviation or
the digital version of it which is
called digital imaging fiber optic trans
elimination device or diffusi from the
terminology digital imaging you could
expect that the image is digitally
transmitted to another monitor and could
be digitally or by your software could
be manipulated by a way and another to
add certain benefits from the software
the idea is very simple okay where light
is presented through a small uh
appreacher in the form of dental
handpiece okay that shines through the
two surfaces showing curious defects
it's as simple as that okay
depending on
that the detection technique
okay of the carious enamel okay
depending on that carious enamel has a
lower index of light transmissions and
sound enamel that's why when light is
absorbed okay through the two structure
it will be
more absorbent when demineralized
process disrupts the crystalline
structure of enamel ending in and that's
why it appears more darken because the
demineralization
absorbs more light this method of keras
detection uses a light source preferably
to be much more bright to eliminate your
tools cares or the mineralized area and
detain or enamel will show up as a
darkened area with this technique this
effect can be achieved with a fibro
optic illuminator which is really
available at the hand beast coupler okay
of your dental operatory to normal
dental units and has been used for
detection of approximate and occlusal
surface as well
0 approximate cares can be diagnosed
with the light probe positioned on the
genes tv
below the cervical margin of the tooth
whereby the light passes through the
tooth structure and the approximate
decay produces a darkened shadow it's as
simple as that okay
although this device has advantage as
the examination is done
with an operating light source already
available in general brackets in your
unit okay
it is only useful for approximate and
occlusal lesions only okay its
sensitivity and specificity are not
sufficient for detection of a very early
carious lesion okay in seventh lesion
okay but much more earlier could not be
detected okay beside of that it is not a
quantitative method that i could score
it or give it an any score okay to be
useful to monitor your cares over a time
that's it it just improves the
visibility of
incident cares in proximally
inaccessible areas
this is the fiber optic transit
illumination device okay you could use
only the handpiece with the coupler in
your unit okay
just to inspect closer and approximate
as shown in a and b photographs
adding a digital component to
your 40 okay
is
a much more
beneficial
option
in your trans illumination as a device
used to detect
early dental cares not only that that
during our discussion we will discover
that it will add as well as qualitative
quantitative scoring of your dental
cares okay it is not only used to detect
dental cares but also it detects
fracture it detects cracks it detects
secondary cares it depicts any
cause of
demineralization it could
quantitatively and qualitatively
count any demineralization or any
defects in your tools structure and
classification of the structure okay it
uses the same
light
of trans illumination okay to trans
eliminate the tools and instantly create
a high resolution digital image okay
this based on the principles that also
carries through tissues scatter and
absorbs more light than surrounding the
healthy tissue that's why decaying near
the emergent surface appears as a darker
area against a more translucent healthy
tissue or brighter background of
surrounded healthy anatomy
the device
just uh composed of a fiber optic
illuminator in a mouse piece okay that
delivers light to one of the two
surfaces
as the light travels through the layers
of enamel and tinting it is scattered in
all directions toward a non-illuminated
surface in the opposite surf in the
opposite side okay and the light is then
directed through the mouse piece
to a nature electronic charged cable
device camera in hand piece and the
camera digit digitally images the light
emerging from either the smooth surface
of the to the illuminated surface or the
occlusal surface okay and transmitted it
to be processed via the software
presence here then your mouse piece will
have two sides okay one is the
illuminator and one is the surface
that's received the scattered light okay
passing through the tools and this is
scattering differs from healthy and
unhealthy
tissues that's why it could be
transmitted into a charged cable device
that camera was charged cable device
that will be digitally transformed into
your cpu and you could process it by a
way or another
decay or cares near the image also
appears darker again is more translucent
and brighter background of healthy
tissue as we discussed before in the
fiber optic trans illumination okay this
image are then displayed on your monitor
in a real time and stored on your hard
drive for easy monitoring and follow up
the case by comparing the images before
and after image acquisition
could be performed and controlled by
software and just would be there just
you are in need to hold your mouse piece
okay and by the would be then you could
click on it and to get different images
every images are viewed in both
clinician and patient side by using a
large monitor with high resolution and
this is useful in patient education and
motivation and sharing the patient the
condition let him imagine
to what extent the destruction or to
what extent the case is hidden in in
accessible areas
one of the advantages of your software
of this device is the average mineral
mineral loss calculation and comparing
between normal and abnormal tissue
okay this device
by the help of this device the average
mineral loss of two structure can be
determined by analyzing and recording
images and assessment of optical
thickness between different stiffness of
two structure of healthy and non-healthy
tissues of the same tools and at
different levels and at different times
so it is considered as a qualitative and
the quantitative diagnostic missile for
the lost tools structure this is a mouse
piece okay
and illustrating where is the
illuminator side and where is the
non-illuminated side okay and this is
the monitor and you could share your
patient identification to identify and
detect okay he could imagine how
much is the destruction of his
the right side schematic diagram showing
that from the eliminator side or the
light source side okay the light passes
through the two structure refracted
reflected and transmitted okay and this
is the scattering of light except for
the area of the effect that scattered in
another way okay helping you to view a
photo okay for this lesion which appears
dark and
normal healthy tissues we could inspect
these uh
resultant
photographs or captured photographs by
the i-40 where in the upper
left side you could note sound proximal
surface from occlusal buccal and lingual
views
the lower left side you could showing
the difference
in darkness in caries proximal surfaces
from occlusal buccal and lingual views
but what is more much more obvious and
clear
and much more descriptive photograph is
the one to the right for carious
occlusal uh
surface
this could
illustrate to you and your patient the
careless legion it's present it's a
presence okay and it's detection okay
advantages of difficulty including its
superior sensitivity over traditional
radiograph
and they can detect early lesion because
later on we will discuss that
radiographs could not detect lesions
unless
it will
cause at least 40 percent
demineralization less than 40 percent
demineralization could not produce as a
required visible radiolucency to be
detected in radiograph but here in di40
the sensitivity is much more accurate
than that for radiograph also the image
could be produced faster okay just you
are clicking your middle you could get
much more frames okay then adjusting
sensor and holding it it's much more
easier for you and your patient an
expense of no radiation and the safety
is much more higher okay
but still
it couldn't differentiate between
carious lesion and the high bone
mineralization and the deeply stained
fishes or even cracks okay it doesn't
show the tips of the lesion
because
light is scattered and accumulated or
collimated to the non-enumerator sites
in two dimensions you couldn't get an
idea about the third dimension you
couldn't get an idea about the progress
of the lesion diagnosis is completely
also based on the observer okay
not
the computer assistance okay it is just
comparing
between old and new picture but it
doesn't score this
demon realization but it as it is
archived in your computer you could you
could compare between
before and after and between
in different time intervals
those all about visual examination we
already discussed the idea of
traditional visual examination how we
standardize is with indices
and how we advance it
with either magnification or trans
illumination trans illumination is
either
just fiber optic or digital imaging
trans illumination let us move to
another technique
for detecting cares as to touching cares
it is a tactile examination of dental
cares tactile examination of dental
caries as stated by jivi black and
operative density book published in 1924
okay he stated that a sharp explorer
should be used with some pressure and if
a very slight pull which is like tucked
back action is required to remove it
then the spit should be marked for
restoration even if there are no signs
of decay then he depends
only okay in a tug back action filled
due to slight resistance of the movement
of sharp explorer along the bits and
fissure and that's all okay
this is how he examining the surface
depending on the surface texture and
surface discontinuity which may be false
discontinuity okay
and the catching was sharp explorer he
stated that it is it indicates curious
lesion and even even if he is wrong this
lesion or this [ __ ] and fisher is
susceptible to carries and you are need
to cut it
into a cavity as a mean of extension for
prevention which is now they not
applicable at all okay
and
already manufacturers designed
different shapes of explorer for to
provide more accessibility to different
areas okay
including cowhorn sharp explorers
including also using nowadays unlike
accidental floss to be passed through
the contact and if it is come threatened
then it meets
a sharp area of your proximal surface
that clearing it indicating that there
is approximate case
the most famous word explorer okay was
marco polo christopher columbus pedro
alvarez cabral fernando fernandez
nel armstrong and one of the most famous
explorer is number 23 explorer dental
explorer it is
more famous than all of these explorers
among dentists okay and it could take
different shapes either angulated curved
uh
contra-angled uh
another curved one cow horn to detect
the proximal cares okay as seen in the
middle figure and you could
use unaccidental frost okay to pass it
inter-proximal this will allow you not
only to examine the approximate area
okay and present for detection of cares
but we use that also as a tactile
examination of the tightness and the
integrity of your contact area for uh
direct and indirect respirations and
also you could use it to examine the
presence by tactile sensation to examine
the presence of overhang margins or
overhanging cement when cementing
indirect respiration
but
when examining dental cares this dental
floss should be unwaxed because the wax
heals the threatening okay all heals
that hearing that we could not inspect
your dental floss okay if it is steered
due to meeting sharp edges or rough
surface of proximal decay
okay but for examining proximal contact
or for examining or to remove
overhanging margins to examine the
presence of overhang margins it is
better to be waxed to allow easily and
the smooth slippage of it along the
contact without damaging your
restoration especially if it is amalgam
which requires
at least at least 24 hours to reach its
complete setting okay
considering the using of explorer
especially
many studies
recommended not to use sharp explorer at
all and the drawbacks of using it is
much more worse than its its usefulness
in detecting dental cares
this is
an old
30 at least
35 years old
study okay
titled light microscopy style study of
the effect of probing an occlusal
surface okay
[Music]
state is that
traditional use of sharp explorer okay
is a questionable matter in determining
dental cares
why but because this sketch
in diagnosis scales in bits and fissure
okay
should be discontinued by clinician
okay and just use sharp eyes and plant
explorer because
even it is non-cavitated it become
cavitated by the damage created by this
sharp explorer okay
another thing who said that who said
that okay that this catch is due to this
continuity of the surface okay it may be
due to
friction between
fissure with parallel walls with the
sides of your explorer okay
even penetration by sharp explorer can
actually cause cavitation in areas that
are starting to remineralize okay
or in areas that could be remineralized
but you already
damaged it okay
also forcing sharp explorer by this not
only traumatized your enamel but also
may force karyogenic microorganism to be
encrypted into your enamel and
while it is it couldn't or it is not
able to produce still not able to
produce dental caries you already give
it a greater chance okay and give it the
chance to produce dental cares and this
light microscopic study just a light
microscope showing this damage okay
a case
to the left the left one a is just a
fissure okay once you are exploring it
was with a sharp explorer okay you could
not the damage
how it comes to your enamel and another
case okay if you move it lateral the
damage extended to the lateral wall this
is just a light microscope study okay in
another
scanning electron microscopic with much
more magnification
effects of dental probing on occlusal
surface
okay a scanning electron microscope
and must in a much more recent study in
2007 okay just you could note
how much is the trauma caused okay as
the arrow pointed to by your sharp
explorer okay and you could note how the
walls are parallel to each other of the
fissure in the photo to the left side
and
inside this square these are the
scratches created by forcing explorer
which is then used as catching or
tuckback action which is diagnosed as
scariest lesion while it is absolutely
sound but you felt tucked back due to
friction between the side walls of your
explorer with the side walls of this
deep fissure another one with higher
magnification showing how much is the
damage
okay
in both sides of your uh
fissure another one showing the damage
of your tip of the sharp tip of your
explorer i wonder how it is not only
breaking
uh
the inter-prismatic substance breaking
your enamel especially in your fissure
okay
is also considered as a weak area
because the sickness of inner it is
improperly coalescent
loops and the thickness of enamel is
very thin at this area okay that's why
it is vulnerable for damage and
vulnerable to create cavitation which is
previously
not the condition before you are using
the explorer this is the head injury of
the tip of the explorer inside enamel
another
one showing you how much the friction
and how much it forces the fragments of
enamel
actually it will force the enamel okay
fragments of enamel and
with
uh or accompanied also with carry using
microorganisms and different types of
micro interference another hit
okay of the head of the sharp point of
your explorer okay was probing marks
okay on the sides that's why most
cardiologists and epidemiologists
recommended the evaluation of presence
of discontinuity of enamel okay or micro
cavitations by the use of who psr probe
which is ball ended one as we mentioned
before when using it in tactile
examination okay with sphere
about 0.5 millimeter okay in its
extremities or in its diameter okay
allowing this kind of evaluation by this
will be much less aggressive and much
less harmful to enamel and it is also
graduated it is used
with periodontist and with
epidemiologists and also cardiologists
because
this bowl plant and prevent this
explorer from penetrating either soft or
hard tissues even when you are exploring
the tips of periodontal pocket finally
those are the textbooks i used in
preparing this presentation please feel
free to ask me at any time as your
questions are welcomed you could ask
any inquiry by commenting to this video
and i will reply to you as soon as
possible also you could email me and i
will reply to you as soon as possible
finally thank you for assigning this
time to listen to me please don't forget
to subscribe to my channel and activate
the notification to get all the updates
thank you yes sir almost
[Music]
you